The likeness meeting for Tuesday April
seventh two thousand and fifteen overheated
and the chair reserves the right to call
items on the agenda out of the order of
the times that are listed for items are
approximate times and Highlands may be
reached earlier or later than the posted
times the listing of items is those
reasonably anticipated by the chair which
may be discussed at the meeting at least
forty eight hours prior to the meeting
not all items listed may in fact be
discussed and other items not listed may
also be brought up for discussion to the
extent from it a final. Seven
pm The board will take
a vote on the Zoning Board of Appeals
new member at seven o five P.M.
Randy scones and Bill Keegan and I will
discuss and we will vote on the fiscal
sixteen operating budget.
Seven twenty P.M.
Randy scones Bill Keegan
and I come we will have
a discussion and vote on the capital budget
for fiscal year sixteen. And at seven
thirty five we will have
a joint meeting with the Board of Water
and Sewer commissioners the advisory
committee and planning board and we will
be discussing warrant Article twenty five
the executive power of town water and
sewer commissioners. That follow with
a few action items. John.
Legend. Of the United States of America
and the Republic with stands one
nation under God indivisible
with liberty just all.
Right. This is opening doors with
a new member we have another packet
of the names or individuals who have
requested consideration so I'm going to
enter these four names into the right.
Of the chairman I would like to make note
that at this time I'll have to recuse
myself from this discussion both because
one of the candidates is my campaign
manager for reelection against me.
So I'll read the four names and then ask
each one of those to their nominating.
Positions alternate. To the
Zoning Board deals. So the
names that we considered
were. Like I'm. Very
sorry that better yet OK. OK so the four
individuals who come forward. Include
Dave Brown. Seventy American way
Kevin Powers forty four
Prospect Street Ari Weinstein
Weinstein one twelve South High
Street and Kurt geisha and five
Oakwood terrors.
So. Each of us could just nominee
who we would like to see.
Named as the alternate we can start it
with with an explanation to the discussion
I'm. Going to first. Love the end
of the table that's where the.
First five thank thank all for
candidates it was I thought it was
a good discussion of the questions were
pretty straightforward and I actually
enjoyed going back to Scotian type interview.
I think I'm partial to David Brock
for that for the following reasons.
I like the fact that he's got
a lot of institutional knowledge
a lot of historic knowledge of the past
projects he's been very involved with the
boards. With the zoning board in the
past obviously but the other boards and
committees and processes that kind of
interact with the zoning board for instance
the. The route one resign
he brought that to
a certain level I think there's still
some work to do on that signed by
a lot he's very very involved in that as
well as the. The new look codified in the
new regulations. The fact that
he goes to the meetings and he's
rejoining for no particular reason other
than he has some knowledge and wants to
share it not to take away from any of the
other candidates but I think at this time
we have one forty B.
That has been submitted and he's got vast
knowledge on that plus you'll find out
that more forty B.
Is coming something that can jump in there
look at the numbers as well as the the
past history I think it comes at
a very good time and I think it fit in there
very well. Thank you know again it was
a good process and thanks to every Kurt
Dave Kevin for throwing their hat in the
ring and giving it
a go. I struggled with this because I
was really torn because the saw the
candidates. Their vision of the town and
how they would conduct themselves lines up
very well with my vision. But at the end
of the day I'm going to go with the
veteran Dave Brown
merely because he brings
a long standing balance to
the position he's. He has
a good reputation and in this particular
case with the issues that are coming
before the town we know what we're going
to get so we're going to put my faith in.
Thanks for. And I want to thank.
Candidates that they came forward. And
I'm going to different different.
I sort through the. Ideas
a little different perspective being an
architect understanding where news is. You
know how. To interact with land planning.
Many. Things David. Came again
I also want to thank all
four individuals who came forward as
potential candidates each one of you brought
a very special skill set I think you
know representing the range of high tech
community focus experience as
a board member in the past and. Also
legal background so I think we were
fortunate to have such
a qualified group of individuals come
forward so thank you. I also selected Dave
Brown as the alternate that I would that
I would support I think. Dave brings
a wealth of experience to the to the Zoning
Board of Appeals and again I think at
this time with the complexities of
what's going on with his E.P.A.
His familiarity with the news
a sign by law that brought me to. Lean
toward stated in this decision so
again I just want to thank all four individuals
who came forward. So it looks like
we have
a three to one selection of David Brown as
our new alternate member for the Zoning
Board of Appeals and we want to congratulate
David and again thank all the other
individuals who came forward.
To. Next time our
discussion on our agenda is
a discussion followed by
a vote for the fiscal year sixteen
operating Fetchit brandied Bill Feig and
advisory committee. Are going to
present information. Good evening.
I'm pleased to learn of present. Will and
I are about thirty percent of balanced
budget tonight sixty five point
nine five million All in
all the rise of. The
insurance accounts etc. It.
Wasn't necessarily
a cakewalk to get to the conclusion here
there were some tough decisions and you
know. We also have had some challenges with
snow and ice as you would expect. We do
plan
a quarter million dollar contingency for
that. As an all out deficit that comes up
the top of next year's taxes but we didn't
need an additional four million dollars
in order to balance this year's snow and
ice deficit and working with the board of
assessors they were. They released
a quarter million dollars to the fund
that that deficit so we want to put in
a position of either way. Having to put
further downward pressure on on budgets
which would have impact of services would
be to something that the state is is
allowing just this year and that is to
roll forward that deficit over three years
which I certainly would recommend that given
that who knows what's going to happen
next year and that happens again this isn't
just about the problem so we saw that
the snow and ice issue. And the
of the school department was
gracious enough they've apparently. Just
getting losing grant funding at this point
in time for their kindergarten program
to the tune of about seventy seventy one
seventy two thousand dollars
and that is that is
a part of their revenue base to support
the program but they have agreed to you
know absorb that within the accounts that
they have. The other accounts and general
fund accounts if they have. It is not
something that terribly comfortable with but
they understand that that's one of components
that we needed this year to to make
everything balance the other big moving
item was health insurance. And although the
the rate hasn't quite settled out yet it
looks like it's getting closer to being
settled certainly sounds like the end of
the month and it sounds like it's going to
settle very close to the number of the
premium increases that we're plan for which
is seven and a half
percent and we did have
a contingency for that just in case. As
far as the state proposal goes we only
saw. The first first car turned over so
to speak out of the seven that you see in
this process and that was the governor's
proposal. And given that we have
a new governor in the proposal
wasn't announced until about
a month ago and we will likely not see any
other information on this between now
and when we got to put this
budget to bed. But in we had
a meeting with the representative there
was today and he doesn't expect that much
is going to change between now and then
Anyways at least on the key items that
impact us which is the education and
the General Government aid so we feel
comfortable with where we are using the
governor's number we've done that fast so
with all that said and some trimming that
the town manager needed to do to budget
requests we were able to come
in on balance and so we have
a balanced budget that's consistent with
our. Range plan keeps us on track for some
longer term objectives that we've talked
about before about some debt service that
we will likely need to incorporate into the
general fund in fiscal seventeen really
related to the next building project so all
in all it took to founts and some good
shape and. I think you'll want to highlight
some of the key changes that we have.
Right Thank you Randy Good evening everyone
and I just want to say up for me also I
think Randy for the tireless number of hours
he put into the process in pulling the
numbers together and I have to tell
you that he made all of our lives
a lot easier by doing the work that he did
and I really appreciate that that effort
and also one thing the icon for all the
hours that they put into the process. Was
relatively a smooth it was
a relatively smooth process and I'm
appreciative of that and in everybody's efforts
to to make that this my first budget
and to be balanced and without
a whole lot of changes in concern so
there are some important items to be
considered in the budget itself that we
didn't we were successful in getting in the
centralized maintenance program first of
its kind here in the community something
that we've been striving for for many many
years so we were able to support that
and to indicate to include that in this
year's spending plan. I'm very very pleased
to be able to do that because I think in
the in the long term it's going to pay us
back to VNS in many many
ways and it also sets us on
a track for for maintaining our most important
assets in the in the buildings that
the buildings themselves. In the most
expensive ass as they should the most
important is our people but having the
the buildings themselves be able to
expensive assets we have to really take
care of them and this actually puts on
a regular plan to do that. Secondarily
I was able to increase some hours in
a couple departments and if some of the
personnel we want to add really new new
bodies per se except when one exception
being in the fired upon we were that we had
of the one captain position but that
position was being paid for with with
ambulance receipts so it's not inside
the the levy put Levy Quezon So as
a result of that action we were able to
increase the I was in the conservation
office by two by some in
a half hour to thirty five hours annually
I thought if I was weekly or out and then
another three hours was added Tuesday to
the sanitariums inspection office in the
office of the what health so we had
a total of ten half hours to cross the
void Now having said that there were
a number of difficult concept had to
make because I think everybody did
a terrific job of advocating for their
positions and they made some excellent case
as to why we should have added additional
positions but simply put we didn't have
the numbers to support that so we'll continue
to keep those things on our radar any
advantage we can support them later while
we certainly will go back and look at
those things and in future years but for
this time I'm pleased to say that we are
balanced and in a way looking
into why sixteen with a with
a spending plan that that I hope we all
can live with so thank you. Just one
question. Snow and ice deficit where it
states that we could be eligible for
a partial Fema reimbursement How much
does that mean I believe the numbers that
I've heard through the fire chief. Works
putting all the details together make the
submissions about one hundred seventy
thousand of something like that. The
challenge with these Fema grants is that
if we do get done they almost always
come too late to provide you know the relief
that we are before the end of this one
year just this past fiscal year we
received money on to fema grants from two
fiscal years prior so it's it ultimately
does come to the town and it flows into
free cash and so it ultimately nets out
to where it would have Anyways it's just
that it's it doesn't it doesn't allow us
to directly you know solve the problem you
know with those dollars but we all try to
get at the interest group that we did one
piece of good news that we can report
that we did receive some what is known as
possible money from the state in the amount
of our ninety two thousand dollars that
was distributed for of
a total of thirty seven million that was
distributed state wide for cities and
towns across the plan Wolf. And I was assured
by Governor Baker just over two weeks
ago we've already Yes we are really approve
the of this we are the paperwork and we
were hit with
a one on the list so we were hopeful we'll
see that will be very very So we're here
actually get out there is that we carry
some of the with the damage that was done
to the roads it's what we would have
any other questions for you. Just
a quick comment and
a general question. Thank you again i'm
did this process looking at all the stuff
that's in front of us started fourteen steps
ago back in the beginning of November
and in the process with the department heads
but it's all it also kept popping out
to the public whether it be the school
committee or board selectman or joint
meetings advisory committees these are all
public processes in this five more steps
to go to get to town meeting so that the I
think the process was very open pulling
out. From the sheets that the overall
expected budget in the receipts receivable
in two thousand and sixteen is
up by the head if you like for
a half percent just generally without going
line by line right you know where is
that coming from. It's coming from taxation
or merrily we you know we're able to
you know grow the the levy limit you know
by two an ampersand There's also new
growth that we've estimated between the
building commissioner in chief assessor and
myself we've just news I think for five
hundred thirty five thousand new tax
dollars for growth new growth in commercial
residential hot combined come by
a combination of everything we have
a grid that we review each year and we
we look back historically at like what's
come in and. You know Bill's very good at
having the best intelligence on what is
likely to pop in time to make it out to
work on to the tax rolls so last year the
number we were estimated was over eight
hundred thousand and it came in just over
over that about eight hundred thirty two
we've usually been very very close never
been way off at least in you know my
tenure here so we feel good about you know
this this number here five hundred thirty
five on the stage there really wasn't
much of a of
a bump there most of it came from. Some
oddities with the charter school formula
and I just don't have
a lot of confidence in that this
point in time given that that's
a moving target that there was think about
a hundred seventy thousand or so from
that and then on the. On the other
sources. Believe we added in net net about
three hundred thousand dollars from free
cash and then as Bill alluded to with
regards to the new fire is ation has been
supported it was approximately two hundred
thousand dollars of incremental emulous
receipts dollars which are sustainable. You
know based on our current run rate that
also came in to be the revenue equation
those are the primary items Thank you
that's
a done for sure thank you really what push
I think I have of yours you know what
you see everything going up
a little bit I know that you're is within
town where you have been able to realize
efficiencies and cost savings
just could you highlight
a few of those just to balance off the
increases I would sure this was one of the.
Health insurance but it was generally
voted shows in general I believe. Are you
talking about that yeah yeah I think with
that with the credits that have been
received through the the the last control
program in essence some of those premiums
have been able to be capped flat net
net. And. You know that there are.
I think the other areas where we're
able to keep it but usually it's
a lot of small budgets
you know there's not
a lot of growth where you can prune away
at them. As far as you know efficiencies
I believe that at the fire contracting of
itself I'm hopeful that that should put
some downward pressure on overtime just
by the way that structured. And that's
you'll see that in the first year you know
how much and when they would be able to
build off of that. I'm not sure
there's anything else because it is
a household insurance result insurance
to. That health insurance is now
unfortunately heading in another direction
and. We've done so much to change the
plan and you know redesign things to put
downward pressure on cost the boards made
some important I mean important decision
to help with that. And so we've we've seen
a downward trend in health insurance it's
because line in the budget and and now
it's starting to go up again because now
we're starting to experience the natural
trend medical cost inflation you know the
way everybody else is but I do believe
that you know there's it's on the town
manager's radar it's if we look at this
again and maybe and we look at you know
the next initiative to how we can try to
you know stop the escalation in that budget
so some of the some of the pressures if
I could just add
a few points that's come across as that are
on health insurance are coming now from
the federal government as well as the some
of the changes in plan design itself. We
were seeing that the dish year the. State
general insurance commissions program
has actually gone up rather dramatically
and they were there face to really look at
redesigning their plan because because
the way the program so it's not it's all
coming in with cost efficiencies there
so they're looking at with redoing their
plan to
a point where hopefully they'll it'll bring
the cost down. It's the the challenge
we face particularly here in Massachusetts
is that we have some of the best health
care in the world and so as
a result it also plays into the cost of
that coverage for most of our employees so
we were really generally faced with
a unique scenario many ways and here in
Massachusetts and this pilot in the with
least the portion of the country because
we have there were many many teaching
hospitals as well as
a lot of research facilities here that
provide some of the best health care.
Providers and services in the country in
the world for that matter so that plays
into that equation but we are going to
continuously look at ways in which we can we
can be efficient on that or that of
course in the whole whole equation we're
looking at. I'm actually serving on the
on the the My avoid for the health the
health trust so I'll be actually having
a lot of say about actual some of the
redesign issues that were that are being
discussed now in the new issue new
directions to looking at so will have direct
input into some into some of those
discussions so let's put some of the other
things that you've asked for was some
of things on the horizon actually quite
exciting in the sense that we were looking
at I know Roger Hill was is here tonight
and you can talk about the the issue of
purchasing our street lights will be able
to buy all our street lights we hope for
there in the in the next twelve months and
then we can actually use those street
lights to our advantage by retooling those
with the new L.E.D.
Lights that will actually save us long
term costs over the next several years in
addition to that will be able to retool
that the dash will heads of those lights
with with technology that will help us to
to read by water meters more with that
with with with wife i type of technology
so that there will again trip about the
cost of getting that information second
there the third thing that I like to point
out is that. By simply owning those lights
we also have the ability to look at that
time my wife I capabilities which is something
that hasn't been discussed but it's
something that certainly could be interesting
to look at over the next few years.
We are continuously having discussions
right now about the trash program that we
don't think that's going to change rather
significantly over the next year would
have an active conversations with that with
the contractors on that piece hopefully
I think we should be able to come to
resolution on that shortly and I'll be able to
announce something to you both of you so
by the way WAY I am encouraged by the
conversations I've had recently so please
do see the call in the right direction.
So. The other item I would I would add
him. Is on the debt service side.
As you know we haven't been adding adding
debt the last couple of years as we
absorbed the debt from the last major
bill building projects this year the debt
service is down about one hundred fifty
thousand excluded debt so that's obviously
a direct sadness to the to the taxpayer
and as I I know you recall the intent of
assuming that the town hall project goes
forward is that because of the savings
that has been generated in in the budgets
over the last four years in terms of
spending well within the limits of the of
the town's you know revenue capacity that
we should be able to absorb the debt service
for the Tao within the general fund
budget which means you know avoiding
a debt that exclusion that's been
a long term goal and. We're on track for
that that was part of the the financial
engineering to this year's budget to make
sure we stayed on plan that we maintain
that bandwidth to to absorb that so I at
least say that we were still right on
track and then the last piece that I think
that's really important to mention is
a fact that we do think that this year we
should be able to come online with the
new solar solar capabilities with
a new solar farm which will go help to
reduce our energy costs on that and. When
the time wired so that will pay for the
tricity cost so. There are some things some
really good things on the forefront of
them we're going to continue to. Have
discussions internally and externally about
how we can do do the job better we're
still learning about the organization and
I think we've made some significant steps
of the right direction
is very severe but still
a lot more to come and I were really pleased
with the progress we've made that you
think. You know first person long. Thank
you for putting this all together I
know it's
a huge undertaking and budget myself so. I
know what's involved I know the sacrifices
a lot of the departments had to make. To
bring in the balanced budget one of my
questions is obviously is what to do the
number on the roads. With with the meals
tax receipts trying to get ahead
a plan how was how can
that impact not only open.
Obligation but these are
going to allow us to spend
a little bit more on roads and in fixing
some of the some of the damages that that
occurred over this winter surely it can you
know the good news is that our chapter
ninety allotment you know will likely
still be at up at the minimum that we
received this year the six hundred ninety
thousand before receiving the additional
three hundred thousand and from the Niels
tax I would putting forward I think it's
probably another two hundred ten thousand
or thereabouts and then we're also
bringing forward forty three thousand
from the prior year that we from meals
tax that we did not appropriate because
if it's dollars It came in you know ahead
of plan so it's now off channeled through
our financials into free cash so that's
why you see another line of
a capital budget putting I think it's forty
three thousand from free cash towards
roads because it was generated from meals
tax and that was the intent as you put it
towards open roads. And I did want to
comment on again another thing that's
been in development and you
know may or may not result in
a kind of discussion by this board about
the use of the all stacks. At the end of
this fiscal year in June we'll update the
actuarial analysis on where we stand with
the unfunded hope have liability.
And that the last time that we were
for that we did that two years ago. You
know we were technically funding at the ARE
WE can you know required contribution
but again that's when we had
a lot of things going in our favor in
terms of downward pressure on cost so I'm
very anxious to see. What this
actuarial report will say
because if we are able to demonstrate
that we're still at the Ark and I'm not
saying. That we will be but if we were to
be then I think that opens up you know
another discussion for the board you know
so you know the plateau the Opeth funding
out of meal stacks and therefore you could
shift more. Towards roads although I
think you know Roger Hill the deep every
director should be part of that discussion
because I think that a million dollars
a year I think you saying that's that's
about all they can handle at this point in
time and so if we were fortunate enough
where our roads funding is is currently at
a at
a nice level so that we can make an impact
on the roads and if our open liability
could be addressed at the arc annually then
there's an opportunity for the board to
discuss something like I'll just throw one
idea out there and it's not mine it's
actually you know there's bills idea and
that was a building maintenance fund as
a possibility but again that's
a policy decision that you know that this
board would take up but so we're hoping
that that with everything that's been done
to date that maybe these two programs
might be reaching the level of funding
that supports them. And there might be an
opportunity to then address the other large
liability that the town has which is
its buildings thank you in. Feels
that to you Jimi. I want to thank
you for the year reign D.
And Bill for
a very smooth budget process. That was
given take. But I think everything
was done feeling and thanks also to the
advisory committee who reviewed the budget
they ask good questions and I wonder can
virtually the manages to present the
budget to me and come they gave for
the answers so I thought it was
a good process. So I went
thank everybody that's.
Tracy Vassily is chairman of the advisory
committee would you like to make any
comments.
Thank you. I just wanted to kind of share
the process I know you often join our
meetings which I thank you all for and just
want to acknowledge the work that Randy
does to help our our whole process go as
smoothly as it does every year and to bill
for and Mary Beth for the work that they
did since January we vetted all the
budgets that's involved that's involved
the liaison's from the advisory committee
of which there is
a lead and then other members meeting
with each of the department heads they in
turn came and the department heads presented
their budgets to the board we did
bring three budgets back for additional
questions and information they were
recreation conservation in the schools and
those follow up discussions went very
well and we did we have completed our
voting on the budget items and all of them
will not unanimous will be recommended
by the Advisory Committee at the Town
Meeting thanks very much to
thank you thank you so. Oh
come on up I'm sure you can
step up and. I thank you.
I just basically have one question for
yourself I'm sorry you have to yeah I mean
you know Larry started six merry way and
speaking on behalf of myself and other
advisers. I guess the basic question
is when we talk about balanced budget
it pretty much means that we're spending
as much as we receive correct so for
maximizing our revenue increase
by forty percent which was
a max. To an epicenter from taxes and
growth on top of that So balance
means that we balance it up by spending
exactly what we came in right. Which is in
me. There's. That's one of the.
Secrets to Foxborough his
financial success without having
a general override says that we do not spend
all of the revenue that we receive you
know we consciously. Design the financing
of the budget to generate at least two
million dollars of free cash and
that's done in the following ways we
under as we under. Fun The local
receipts dollars that we take
in that's all the fines fees permits payment
of taxes Motor Vehicle Excise to the
tune of a million
a half dollars every year based on our
estimates about sixty lines and you can
usually come pretty close on and then there's
another of the half million that will
trickle in from unspent budgets because
they cannot be spent it cannot be overspent
so they have to be there understand
a spat at all that the level their budget
and then changes on our balance sheet and
this year we actually. Went further below.
Our revenue. By one million nine hundred
fifty thousand local receipts so we've
estimated local receives to grow to a
certain level but we've only committed
a proxy to me in less than that OK so
that's good information that I may not have
known so the four to have percent increase
in revenue represents how much money.
Roughly three million bucks three million
profit so what did expenses grow by.
In total Well yeah is it the same with it
I mean half its balance it has to be the
same so the expenses rose by three
million also. So would we save money.
Is this say I thought your point was is
that we spend everything that we have. My
point is we increase the revenue by three
million dollars and we spent an extra
three million dollars as acar No I mean
right revenues could support an incremental
. Two million dollars in spending OK but
we but we don't we choose not to spend
that so that the real reason we do that
is in order to provide the financial
flexibility to the town so that when times
are hard meaning like state aid declines
or other other receipts decline that we
count on that we're able to maintain what
has consistently been
a policy direction from both the boards
like and school committee to maintain
services I.E.
Operating budgets and cut back
on capital to defer those those
purchases in order to maintain maintain
services so we don't we don't fluctuate you
know revenues drop by
a million dollars And therefore we have
five million dollars to cut we maintain
a reserve just by under budgeting of revenues
that we have so that we can maintain
some consistency of services case there I'm
just I haven't heard the number yet so
the fourth have percent increase in
revenue was how much. I mean you know.
Three point one three
point one Total. OK in
a committed revenue in the community OK.
But what about in total non-committed is
what it is again approx me another two
million dollars on top of that so that's
done for free cash that yeah that will
ultimately flow from cash I could think you
know. Taking any other
questions. I'd like to thank
Bill Mary Beth and Randy for doing such
a great job and also for the thanks to
the school for many that you know the
history of collaboration between them
in this bill budget side and the school
budget side has done the town well we really
appreciate your efforts and also thank
the advisory committee for their many hours
and their in-depth analysis always very
interesting to listen to some Thank you
mention I just I just would be remiss if I
didn't they also thank the school committee
in their efforts meetings with them
have been extremely productive.
In that it's it's no lie that
it's no secret rather that the that this
committee provides an excellent value for
throws with from the education the education
program has is extremely highly rated
and I think they do
a terrific job with what they have and. To
get in there as if they could value for
the dollars in their program so I'm very
pleased with the work really ship that we
have and I hope it continues I hope I know
is continuing to well in the future. And
it also sets us to
a missed statements out there we had one
more risk that I'd be remiss if I didn't
say this it's been kind of
a pet peeve for five years now and. Talk
about the meals tax and it is going up and
I think we if you remember when we voted
on this at town hall it was we had certain
projections at the meals tax because it
was new or is it one percent. And the
reason I think that it passed
was because we said it is
a tax and nobody likes tax
but if it was going to be
a tax it was going to go to our future the
OPAP it was going to go to our roads and
now it seems like we're getting. You know
the state continues to be level with
their money that comes in for this for the
roads plus we have all this revenue for
the meals tax plus it's more
than we thought if we make
a change in his apologies to change that
and we're changing it from OPAP which is
paying the retirement. For the people
that are here today at town hall plus the
generations before before we take it away
from that and take it away from roads and
put it towards other thing
I think it has to be
a robust discussion at
this table and not just
a quick question if you were here at that
hearings in which it just sort of those
discussions I think we've been steadfast
in our approach to say oh yeah I've been
using words My point is other
a mess if I'm adamantly against spending
it on anything else entertaining me now
that the discussion but I don't want to
be just able put it out there and discuss
it because it's
a new idea but I'm. All right you know I
think I just I think just to be clear
about that I think what really IS point
is that if we're able to address those
items adequately have money left over the
question is What do you want to do with
the reserve and I think that's the core
conversation we want to have with everyone
here I mean I don't think we're not going
to we're going to just take on that
decision in him do that without without
it with discussion with everyone because
it's an important policy discussion and
those so the only thing that we've
introduced to for consideration which we
have when I even there yet because we
haven't even we don't have all of the
information for all the pieces but if we end
up in
a place where we do have some additional
capability there the question is are there
other areas that you want to dedicate them
for the funding for provided that you're
with rescue or could rescue no one when we
have that discussion once we have better
information on the Oprah book do you believe
the actuarial results will usually be
done you know by the end of the. Calendar
year and I just want to clarify I have
a vague. Sense of incorrect messages I
don't see us moving away from the seven
hundred thousand
a year funding very currently for hope
have I see that needing to continue at
a minimum you know
perpetuity. Thank you. To
get the most you are nuts but.
I move the border so what will
accept the fiscal year two thousand and
sixteen budget as presented actually this
is a bit of
a myth and so is it with operating
the operating. Thank you discussion
both as
a favor and I thank you.
Thank you. Happy couple
but it. Still be. Kept me me again
this year as it always does and soon all
the requests all the departments and. All
of the requests are able to be funded
with the exception of for. The end of the
total supported was two point five two
point four million dollars. And there was
a good list of items from a variety of
different departments I know you have
a copy of of the article. But
there are some good there was
a real significant give and take.
And I think in particular I think
really want to talk about. The D.P.
Gov director and how he made it all work.
Because I'd just like to to knowledge of
Roger Hill and his is the pilot for taking
a step back so we could see some other
important issues such as the lighting for
the field be addressed this year or in the
future no it's an important opportunity
it will put the window for that
consideration and that again
a very collaborative process which we were
able to address really all the items on
the on the list this year which doesn't
usually happen so I think. The thing is it
was
a great process really appreciate everybody's
effort to try and get to that final
moment and know that as is tradition with
funding our non building capital needs
and no borrowing required to do that all
funded from cash or and just needed you
know grants like chapter happened I
didn't have that so no no debt issuance.
I just want to say that I thought the
process was really great. One we had again
Tracey the silly from the advisory committee
bill branding myself and Roger and
Spinelli. From the school and. The outcome
I think it's terrific that we again thank
you Roger for your. Innovation and likes
ability for making this happen so anybody
have any questions on any particular
items. And. I'm of the Bourse
what's been approved Article five
the two thousand and sixteen C.I.
He budget is presented can. You discuss.
All those in favor. If you.
OK The next item on our agenda is the joint
meeting Board of Selectmen with water
and sewer commissioners and advisory
committee and planning board.
Water and Sewer commissioners do you want
to come up in front of your. Bench if I
could just take
a few most help and try and frame the
discussion for those that would be home grown
away for when you get your
first but if you think you're.
Going to get.
Three. Just as
a first. Order ready to produce the draft.
Maybe you need even if you
want to call your meetings or.
Yeah. But from what I'm wearing
a suit which is meeting for. Two
Tuesday the yes seventh of. April
twenty fifth. Thank you. Bill would you
like to thank you do other or any other
boards that want me to call that means the
world and all the planning board is here
. When they all said.
I could get Fred off.
Thank you and add comment I was here with
him MC I come here as well so so thanks
everyone for being here
tonight and this is
a important discussion so much so that I
I specifically asked for additional time
to sort of get this the issues out in the
forefront tonight because ultimately this
is an important policy consideration which
I know that we all have some of points
things to talk about. So just to
frame this discussion this is
a discussion about. The executive powers
of the town water water and sewer
commission which just to get
a little bit of history apparently was
altered in June two thousand and thirteen
through
a change in the in the charter I was I
wasn't here during that period of time so I
can't really speak to the specifics of what
happened but all I know is that the it
was it was later discovered that there was
a concern about whether or not that the
change that was made went further than what
was fully intended to happen that was to
a missionary trying to just allow the Tommies
you have authority over the personnel
and in the in the water sewer commission
on the ones who commission that would hope
would be in as good as by the D.P.W.
. It's my understanding that discussion
that to change the member that was that was
done actually one perhaps a little
bit further than that and as
a result that's the reason why this this
motion this this action is here tonight. I
think in further than that is it that
there's been further discussions about the
sort program and in the end that the changes
that have been forthcoming with the
new program or any of that added capacity
that the town now has as part of being
part of the regional So a program with
no one in Mansfield and so therefore
a lot of the town to have some additional
capacity in it that will allow us to to
address many of the economic development
issues that the town has been looking to
try to address for many many years so
with that in mind there's been some
discussion about the possibility of selling
some capacity outside the borders of
the time which for for really well intended
reasons I understand why the the in
the discussion is taking place obviously
to address some of the finances associated
with this with the with the the with
participation the new plant and the debt
service that goes along with with Optus
a patient. So with that in mind I think
the there are three important issues that
we really need to try try and discuss and
try to bring some resolution to tonight
and that is the issue of finances and I've
asked many scholars to be here tonight
to actually address some of the issues of
the finances so we're clear on what the
finances actually mean when the payments
are do how much debt service is involved
here so we can actually have the ability
to to explain that to everyone so
everybody's fully on board about what that
truly means. And into the issue of The
Long and short term strategy for Ford
So we use so that we know over the long
long short term what are the needs that
need to be addressed from the town in that
you know how we are we fully considered
all those those those prospects before we
consider the sale of. Some capacity
outside the borders and then third of
course of that is the authority the SO
Commission has has in WA and should continue
to be the in my opinion industry it's really
my opinion they have the authority to
sue over the sale capacity within the system
and in particular even within the town
the question really that's be forced
tonight is whether is is should there be
a check and balance in
place for the sale of so
a capacity if it goes outside the borders
of the town and perhaps and then if that
is in fact true it should if there is
a need to do that what should that mechanism
be so there isn't anybody here tonight
that I know of that really has
a set. Solution to this and I think really
what we have to talk about is first of
all is there an issue number one in two if
there is how we address it so I doze or
three bullet points I think that we really
need to try to address tonight so to
understand the finances of this I think
that's really important because I give the
credit all the credit to the to the so
a commission for making sure that where
they are being cognizant of the rate payers
and as we all are I think I don't get it
there's anyone in the room that doesn't
get
a call to say that but there it's for for
it's it's really in the forefront of their
minds that it has to be addressed
and we don't result in
a situation I could get expensive for the
rate payers and we're all on the what
about that the question is what's the
right way to address that and I'd like to
turn over three a possible say
a few words about. Good
evening again.
I was asked to. Take
a look at the. Debt burden that the.
Water enterprise. Will be responsible
for. The once the the permanent
financing is just put in place. For the for
this project the expansion of sewer as
well as the. Renovation of the
existing plant and so I've reviewed
the financing docu are they that
modeling documents. That have been
worked on by the. Consultant for the for
the water and sewer commissioners and
my take on the financing obligation
that we're looking at in summary is.
Leave the number that we will likely our
share of the number that will likely need
to pay the debt service on
that proximately five and
a half million dollars. Five and
a quarter of that is the town's share of
all of the enhancements and expansion to
the plant and then there are some other
costs in addition to that that Nance field
is absorbing for the
other regional M. And F.
And and then they will likely load that
on to the debt that is file that is
initially. Issued in approximately
fiscal two thousand and
eighteen and about another quarter million
dollars rough and tough should bring the
total principal debt service that will
be responsible for for about five and
a half million dollars And again the
understanding is that it would likely be
issued and physically seen by the regional
districts our share would you know would
be our responsibility we would have to go
out to buy to want for it we would just
submit our debt service
payments. To the regional.
And again so it's we're talking approximately
three fiscal years out before the
debt service. Would start
and the over the next five
years if you look out five years. Our
total debt service assuming you know two
point four percent interest rate which
could be even better depending upon the
financing that the regionals is
able to get would be just less than
a million dollars over the next five
years zero over the next two and about
a million dollars over the
following three so but
a million dollars roughly just under that
over the next five years and what I've
done on this on the stand out is. Just
try to equate that to how much capacity
would would need to be sold in order to
just handle the debt service. And that
would be approximately twenty three thousand
gallons at that the price that's been
discussed by the water and sewer commissioners.
And as you can see I chalked out
the schedule and you know five year
increment so you could see how much of the
hundred seventy thousand gallons that is
being acquired here I would need to be
sold over time just to handle the debt
service and as you can see it's currently
it's at twenty seven year schedule that
can change depending upon how the the
Regional of me wants an
issue the debt would be
a thirty year schedule to be twenty five
years schedule or probably something close
to this so I feel it's
a pretty good proxy so it's not that we
have to it's sell one hundred seventy
thousand gallons right out of a
gate or come up with five and
a half million dollars out of the gate you
certainly have to come up with that that
money plus the interest about seven point
four million dollars over twenty seven
years but as you can see it's something
that we would need to find over time it.
Quicker it. Altered
back over to you to the
perhaps we could maybe like to hear from
that sort of pushed as to why what that
what their thoughts are on this with OK
Thank you Bill First off any questions from
anyone from Randy at this point.
There's more copies of your two.
Any questions plenty of. OK
ready. On the number so so when you get
to twenty here twenty twenty you say it's
about twenty three thousand gallons that
you need to sell to breakeven for the
payments for that and then we get five
years later there's another thirty six
thousand gallons is that on top of your
slightly top of so you cumulative so the
total of the the the gallon column is hundred
seventy thousand of capacity that is
the entirety of what's being purchased in
the experience over the next twenty seven
years you have broken it down intervals
of five years twenty two thousand thirty
six thousand basically around thirty
thousand gallons correctly year over five
years and in the. The reason I broke
it out like this is because I
understand and I can appreciate the.
Concern of having to come up with
all of this money certainly on the we
certainly wouldn't want to put this burden on
the existing sewer rate
payers I know that's a that's
a feeling that the waters are commissioners
are guarding against religiously from
the from the beginning here but what I
wanted to show is that at least over the
next five years if this is the debt
service that would be looking at it for
whatever reason there was an inability to
sell those twenty three thousand gallons
over the next five years that the town
treasury certainly has the capacity within
its cash balances in order to could loan
you know that million dollars to the
the water and sewer of the sewer
enterprise so that that's
a possibility I just want to I don't
want the policy boards here to be making
decisions without knowing that you know
we do have ways to do the short term fund
within our own Treasury the Treasury has
in any given day anywhere from fifteen to
thirty million dollars that we have and
were allowed by law to to mingle you know
those funds they're all accounted for
separately in our ledgers but you can mingle
them and so we are allowed to to offer
you know this relatively short term
amount of money and until the in also
related but not knowing what's on the books
a potential development in or out of
town if developments came on housing
developments or retailer supermarkets or
whatever and also and in four years they
wanted to bring eighty thousand gallons
into the town or into his field and beyond
that it's almost like paying your mortgage
off early you could. Bill for that and
get that added revenue early and pay
off it early right now and I think the
commissions are probably feel
a lot more comfortable having that cushion
in the bank because at the end of the
day they still would have to come up with
you know the seven roughly seven point
four million over the over the twenty
seven years and include the interest so
selling eighty thousand is great but they
still ultimately need to sell hundred
seventy just in order to cover to cover
the debt service but the near term
concerned I I believe is and my my opinion
is minimized in the next five years
given that the town certainly can and work
with the with the commissioners to make
sure that you know there is no
unfortunate rate raising That's
a worst case scenario that's if there's no
new customers coming in to buy this flow
correct OK Thank you. For the
finance related question.
Might. You like to. Make
some comments or give us
a statement. And the only
thing I'd like to say is.
I think we're doing
a disservice to the voting public by taking
two very important issues and confusing
them they warrant an article is to clean
up legislation that was misrepresented
has nothing to do with the sale at so
capacity whether it be in town out of town
and I've personally wrestled over the past
few meetings with the fact that we've
had this issue of the authority of the
water and sewer commission and we seem to
find ourselves talking about the sale of
sewer capacity. This issue needs to be
addressed and cleaned up and whatever
conversations need to be had about the sale
so
a capacity should be had and I think the
opinion of this board at least myself is I'd
be more than happy to have that conversation
with anybody and everybody but we need
to stop introducing the article to one
article as if it has anything to do with the
seller so it begs the whether be in
town out of town because even as
a board member sitting on it I find myself
to be somewhat confused if the public
needs to understand one has nothing to
do with the other there is an issue with
authority whether. A legal opinion that
this board has the authority to ever
really do nothing now if there is
perceived to be the intention when I was
put into place back in December of two
thousand and twelve. I don't think anybody's
of that opinion that it was ever set out
to completely strip the water and sewer
commission of all authority and at least
from our perspective the only way to clean
that up is to go back in and not add
anything to it not mess with it but make it
right and that's the way we
presented. The war an article and
hope that everybody will support it and
any issues as far as who's buying sewer
aware should be sold more than happy to
have that conversation but let's let's get
this resolved.
With the playing board like to
make any comments this time.
Well just in terms of the master plan we
just we are only concern is that. All of
us view. That this new sewer capacity as
a town asset and that you know the town
spent a lot of years and a lot of money on
a comprehensive wastewater treatment plan
probably needs to be relooked at some
point once we know that we have the the
the full flow from from the I.M.F.
The good news is that once we
once we you know signed the I am
a you know we're now longer going to be
dealing with household uses based on Title
five it's going to be actual
flow which is going to be
a big benefit to homeowners
and so it's going to be
a big benefit to any potential
growth in the town. So just from
a planning perspective we just want to make
sure that everybody in the town who is
in the critical needs areas or is in an
economic development area gets taken care
of before we deal with any future sales
to any entity that's outside of our
borders and that's that's that's our only
that's not only dog in the fight which
really isn't
a dog in the fight we just want to make
sure that you know the town comes first if
there is you know additional flow at some
point in the future that we all feel as
a community is going to be
a benefit in the war so we're commissioners
you know want to deal with that and the
Board of Selectmen is
a part of that decision and I'm sure we
would support that. That that's really
that's really our perspective on it we
want to make sure that all that that will
the time we're putting into this new master
planning and the other state you know.
Planning issues that are going to come to
for you know get paid attention to and
that we take care of all that stuff
that's that's our basic concern.
Yes you just like just like comment on
which is which is quite good I thought I
thought you did nice job just explaining
what the real there really is two issues
of play here one is the authority that
goes through the commission and I haven't
heard anyone really say that that's really
a question that they that they want to
return the authority to that to the
commission I guess the real question
remains though what mechanism would be in
place to assure that
a further discussion will be held relative
to the sale of capacity also the Tao If
in fact there were to occur and there's
no guarantee that you're going to happen
you may not even have a
what mechanism would be
a place to do that so that I think
everyone has of assurance that further
discussion is had before that actual
action took place I guess that I pose
a question back to the Commission if they
could address that. Propose something I
don't think were opposed to anything only
contention is that it doesn't belong in
this legislation this needs this this
was missed misconstrued and needs to be
cleaned up so let's clean it up the way
it should be and well and didn't want to
taint anything. We said at least from my
personal perspective came in front of the
Board of Selectmen at least four times
and advance of signing the I am me and I
don't see why we would go about in any other
way or anybody else for that matter in
oppositions. Again you know I
think I said it earlier I'm not
a plow I have the conversation with anybody
that's well and have it appreciate that
thank you Madam Chair just I just that not
to I want to introduce Kay Conley who
was here on the town council tonight
representing the town of course and its team
made
a Sue was actually sort of special counsel
to soar water commission he said tonight
too so I did and Roger all of course of
who was here to join us as the Commission
into the deal to direct it
I guess that I would pose
a question to either one of the
counsels through do you have a perhaps
a legal mechanism that could be done that
would assure folks that if in fact that
were to happen is there
a way to do that that was so we wouldn't
complicate the legislation but I think
anybody here would not looking to try and
make it complicated but we need to have I
would think some to some assurance at least
that's my understanding of this issue
that there's a further discussion before
a sale of some of those would be sold
also the borders. I made it to the chair
Steven but I was so miles will call special
counsel. Before I turn to the managers
. The question that he posed if I could
just frame put this in context perhaps it
may be helpful. I was brought in when
those water and sewer commissioners were
negotiating on the district agreement
for the new sore district and that
legislation and was somewhat surprised
to learn of all the special acts that
Foxboro has relative to soar operations
but the history that I'm sure the cycling
are probably all familiar with probably
more familiar than I am is that the one
store commission was empowered by Special
Act in one nine hundred eighty four I
believe and they they have or and I'm sorry
nine hundred eighty six chapter forty
six of the acts of nine hundred eighty
six and he gave to the water and sewer
commissioners all the authority previously
held by the select board to operate the
swore operations in town and that's
how it's operated ever since the
town manager act in.
Two thousand and four.
May have cast some doubt about the authority
of the commission but then there was
a subsequent special Act in two thousand
and ten that confirmed their authority as
originally established in the one nine
hundred eighty six act and so that's how we
were proceeding on least since I've been
around working on the district agreement
and then I became aware of this tweak
if you will to the town manager act in
December of two thousand and thirteen
which specifically cited the one thousand
nine hundred six enabling authority of the
commission and and it seemed to. Almost
know of by all the authority of the
commission with this new two thousand and
thirteen act and when I mentioned it
to the director Roger Hill that I was
surprised about of this recent amendment
and that I thought it now clouded all the
authority that the commission had he said
no that's not what it was supposed to do
it was supposed to just confirm at the time
at the time managers authority relative
to personnel and collective bargaining
powers or on behalf of the town relative to
water and sewer commission employees and
I said well because I was reviewing this
in anticipation of that the commission may
be entertaining because that's always
been the proposal relative to funding or.
Holding current rate payers harmless from
the cost of the treatment plant improvements
that are coming down the pike if you
will that we would gain this asset that
we could sell and so I was expecting
anticipating that I would probably have to
issue an opinion or the commission would
have to warrant represent in any transaction
that they are doing authorized to
enter such
a transaction and I And so when I saw this
two thousand and thirteen Amendment I
said wait
a minute this is our our authority now
is not so certain and as I said Mr Hill
inform me that that was never the intention
and so with that I simply drafted what
I thought was
a relatively brief and non-controversial
clean up if you well to just confirm that
what was adopted in two thousand and
thirteen did not intend to strip the
commissioners of their authority relative
to. All sewer operations and ability to
sell capacity that they certainly had from
the eighty six act and the two thousand
and ten act and then it with
a new town council very collegial
entertaining that I understood the board of
selectmen were concerned about some they
wanted some oversight now learning perhaps
that they may have gained some authority
that they didn't have previously with the
thirteen I'm not I don't know if that's
a fair characterization of it but the
commissioners strong opinion back to me was
there was never any intention for the
Commission to give up its authority and that
the thirteen Act should be clarified so as
I have with town council tried to broach
the topic is there somewhere we could
go. And the answer has been pretty
resoundingly no was never intended we
never intended to give anything up and
therefore. They prefer my original proposal
to restore the status quo if you will
so that's that's my kind of background as
to why we're here with relative to that
article. But between the parties if
there's if there's anything that would be
entertained of course I'd have to leave
it to the commissioners as to. Where they
could go or what they could consider. This
time. Around So turning that house and
I have spoken about this and we are in
agreement that there is
a legal way to do either of these of four
to clarify the authority either way or
for the one way the board's both concluded
you want to go and we've come up with
several different proposals
but it comes down to
a policy decision that's that's not
a legal decision we can help you. Which you
know with whatever language needs to go
into one article to clarify and we agree
with his legal opinion previously that
there was some. Marking of the waters if
you were with respect to the authority of
the water and sewer commission by that
twenty thirteen Amendment so I think the
boards do need to decide how they want
to handle this and then we can make the
proper language exceptions to clarify the
previous special legislation for twenty
thirteen through new special legislation
Thank you. Bill you mention one other
aspect for us to discuss as we're working
on this recurring long and short term
strategy. Right with respect to the long
or short term strategy I mean I was
referring I think
a lot of that was clarified the other
evening at least to my mind from the mini
with the with the master plan discussion
that occurred just last week that there is
a lot of capacity potentially here in the
in that the question is when is that
they're going to come on line because
at the end of the day they the water so
commission are primarily concerned with
making sure that that they're selling
capacity and that capacity is going to be
able to pay for the for the for the new
plant as it comes online and is Roger Hill
and I have discussed too that you know
what he'd like to have some money that
could actually help bolster the fund the
revolving fund there are
a LOT him to do some additional I and I
work in the end to help pay for some of the
other expenses associated with with providing
additional capacity into the system
so having said that. The question that then
comes into mind are we going to. What's
the best mechanism that we can have in place
where the both would feel comfortable
that we're taking the right steps I think
it's very clear that there is that the
goal of the little waters with which you
want the status quo retained but I think
the remaining question is what's the level
of comfort that that the sale that that
there is we've got in the sale of capacity
also are the boards committee will be
fact we know based upon I mean it was
held this past week that there's
a lot of potential for the Belmont right
within our own borders and is what is that
Dubai is by selling their capacity outside
our borders those that in fact. Somehow
jeopardize the future development of our
community that we go so that's really the
question that we have to wrestle with you
is boards of policy makers is a really
a policy decision we'll try to help you
get there but ultimately you have to give
us guidance away one of those. Larry.
Larry Thomas six Norton street private
citizen I'm just wondering why. So currently
the way it is is anything outside the
district but in the town goes to town meeting
why not have it so that anything outside
the steward district goes to town meeting
whether it's at
a town or in town and that that is the check
and balance I think that everybody is
looking for so it doesn't come to the
select and but it goes to the town whether
it's you know out of state not made out
of the town or in the town so are you
saying that it was
a project Saddam Hospital was when there
was so slow to that developer that that
particular question we're going to find
Tommy Yes Yeah I mean I think I'm pretty
sure that's what we that's what we passed
in the fall of two thousand and thirteen
with that in anything outside the
sewer district whether it was
a business or whether it was
a private residence had to go to town
meeting. So I mean at that to tell you the
truth at the time you know as an outcome
or when I voted for this I really thought
that that also pertained to out of town
I didn't know that out of town was yet
a third category you know
we have in District at
a district in town out of district and
out of town that third category I never
realized was
a separate category so you. Want to look
which is limited only to the suit district
Thank you yes yes and that's Yes I mean
you know the discussions that we had was
that this was such
a valuable asset to the town that the
town really should speak on how it's used
thank you thank you. And you should.
Say as as a selectman I was
intrigued by the I.M.F.
. Process and I began attending water
meetings because I just wanted to learn
what was going on what the I Am A was the
into municipal agreement you know so I
tended on this two years I've been attending
meetings. And I I was very much for
the the I Am Me it because I think that
the town deserves the ability to develop
commercially and to help residential
residents who with failed such
a septic system but I think the main
goal in my mind was for our economic
development because right now the downtown
area where our fights Phil was are
Bradley the old brothers posit the
a limited in what can go in there
because of flow issues so for two
years I've been I've been
listening in and. There were.
Talks about. Sharon's comments and
the tally Sharon was mentioning.
And I went to I was at
a meeting and I and I there were two other
board members of another board were
there and when Sharon can
sound to Sharon Clements as
a possibility you know to sell flow the
three of us said you can't do that that's
going out of town you're selling an asset
I've attempted before anybody in town has
had the ability to purchase it. So
when these one articles came up
I was assigned to do the to look into it
for from the boys like men because I'd
been going to the waters were meeting so I
was familiar with it and as I read it I
realize that they. What was
housekeeping tweaking it to
give the water and sewer. Authority
to do contracts you know executive
authority situation to change all of
it I mean and this is the project of
unintended consequences right right now
it's neverless whether water and sewer can
do
a conference. Right now according to the
attorney probably Bush workman has asked to
have him so that's one problem
but then you have the idea here
that the possibility of selling an asset
of the town sewage to it to another town
to help them develop economically and for
the for housing and I said to myself Wait
wait
a minute this is this is something that
should be that should be looked at
not. Because it's an asset not just
by the water and sewer but wait
a minute maybe another thought he should
OK it are you know go along with that.
Because when when the
I Am A was present at
a town meeting and we except it the town
meeting was told that no one could look
into the sewer system unless they got to
town meeting approval and that was very
important because I don't believe that
the thing would have passed without that
proviso that town meeting approval
had to be given in order to to.
Go to with this become part of the source.
However nothing was said about oh by the
way see I am a gives us one and
so are the authority to do
a contract to sell sewage outside the town
without anybody's approval town meetings
or going without anybody's
approval and I went Wait
a minute that's that's
a little different I think I
think we have to say it's take
a step back and say what are we doing with
this very important asset of this town
are we going to allow it to go out with to
be sold outside of town without somebody
else saying yes that's OK or I don't think
so we don't want to do that so yes there
are two issues there are two issues. And
I think in order I think both of the
issues have to be have to we have to have
a solution to both the issues before we go
to town meeting. Because I won't support
that one out of vote unless there
is some mechanism that gives
a check another check on some
possible sale of flow outside of town
you have town meeting history prove
inside towns Well I think this should be
something as Larry said he the town meeting
our sound check for selling it outside
town because it's an asset to the
town it's been characterized as
a liability at five point five million
dollars liability Well yes we own five point
five million dollars but we don't know
what on Thursday we don't start paying it
for
a few years and Randy has explained that
it is doable even if we don't so all the
flow right away it is doable town can
handle it I think I'm afraid that that
the the impetus to sell flown in order to
protect the town and I understand water
and sewer is concerned about about the money
I understand that but what I'm saying
is wait
a minute let's wait to see if the people
are into these inside town want to buy
this because the number one hundred twenty
five thousand gallons has been bandied
about in more from one of the one place.
If we if we have one hundred seventy five
thousand gallons that we have we have
purchased from Mansfield and you deduct that
hundred twenty five thousand gallons from
that you have fifty thousand gallons.
With fifty thousand gallons if you will if
you if you if you want to develop spill
clouds or
a breath these plans are are we have if
we have come in and that's only fifty
thousand so that was that was
my concern. My concern is is
we should have a check as we have
a check and balance for for adding for
going into the system inside town but
then we should have
a check and balance of the product possibility
of selling fall outside the town so
this is two different issues in the end I
understand that but I would but like I
said I would not support that the war in
Iraq and tweaking unless we have like
a side letter or an agreement or
something that that there would be
a check and balance on possible
outside town sale or they. Can.
Share from. Your own life of
forty three grants really
just to in order to address some of the
Lowry said first of all just as an aside
here that the two potential forty B.
That are on the docket now one that's
already been filed and the second one which
was just filed today those alone will
be the large one if it was to pass the
C.B.S.
Authority at Fisher Street is just slightly
under forty eight thousand gallons it's
about a million
a right there and then Mr Lynch is and
he's Foxboro has about thirty five hundred
gallons so between the two of them it's
over two million dollars You know right off
right off the bat to address any concerns
about how do we begin to make payments I
don't think Andy Randy would ever have to
make the loan you know to get us to get
a started. My concern with what would with
a lot reset is you know in terms of the
economic growth picture for the town of
Foxborough or any town today. As if the F
A project of any size wants to come to
your town they want to know want to advance
what their potential is they don't want
to know that it could be hanging in the
balance of town meeting which we all know
can be a very it's a great form
of government but it can be
a very fickle form of government as well
it's very difficult to get two or three or
five hundred people to all
agree that that plaza is
a terrific idea or that new
biological buildings going to be
a great idea wherever it might be so you
know I'd be more inclined I just as
a citizen I'd be
a lot happier if I knew that there was an
arrangement in that particular kind of
case between the wars commissioners and the
executive branch or whatever where it's
more finite group that can make
a decision about the economic future of our
town instead of you know just laying it
out there and waiting for an annual meeting
or I September or November or January
me whenever it's going to come because I
think that you may miss opportunities for
economic development if we if we work
on that basis thank you thank you.
Very. Very Weinstein one twelve
South High Street I'm reading.
Mr Hill's. Letter to the Foxboro patch of
October eighteenth of twenty thirteen he
explains to the people of Foxboro why we
should be entering into the I Am A All of
the. Explanations given involve.
Dealing with issues in town
none of them involve selling flow out
of town. I would say that I agree
with this cupolas. Point that the there
should be some checks and balances
regarding the sale of flow outside of town
but I would say that should also include
a sale
a flow outside of the district. Gentleman
from the Planning Board just said that.
People want to know ahead
of coming in to make
a bid on building something in town whether
or not they're going to get that flow I
would say that the the handover group
already knew well before we'd even entered
into the I Am A from the water and
sewer commissioner and from the D.P.W.
Chief that they were going
to get that flow it was
a parcel of land that was excluded so.
You're not going to lie you seem to do an
awful lot well I mean we don't we don't
want to we want to break this not we'll get
Will you leave it up to respond but I will
be going to I don't know how they would
think that they were going to build five
four storey buildings in that development
without the knowledge of being able to
get flow seeing as the extended stay was
limited to ten thousand gallons
of septic and flow wasn't even
a possibility there because that wasn't
part of the district it seems possibly that
the I am a map has been altered to change
it so that it says that if it's a forty B.
Somehow it's now in the district even though
the I may maps that it was not part of
the district representative Barrows knew
about this proposal two years ago before
we entered into the I may
or even discuss the I am
a. There's been at least three different
explanations on different occasions by
water and sewer and D.P.W.
As to what the flow capacity in the
source of the flow are meetings that I've
attended. It seems to me that
this this development on
Fisher street is very much
a big part of the concern
here. I'm sure my stand said
in
a personal conversation with one of our
neighbors and I'm paraphrasing here why are
you people fighting this it's
a done deal he emailed on January
twenty first in response to.
Visitation to meet in the January twenty
seventh meeting held to clarify the water
and sewer issues at Town Hall and
I'm quoting directly here this is
a group of aggrieved to butters using every
irrelevant argument they can come up
with to stop a forty B.
Housing project I'm not playing this useless
and unproductive game Thank you let me
give you all
a nickel's worth of advice can see that
this is going to be built so I would say
that it sure does seem like people already
do know what they're going to be given
here and that's deeply concerning to me and
still wants to. Test yet he is you know
just like this I appreciate your comments
but this is really not relevant to this
particular discussion I think
it is because I think as
a resident of the community I understand
I would like to see some checks and
balances oids the OK that's that's
a fair point OK but I think and this is
what I would like when we joke but we don't
want to get into a
discussion about a forty B.
Prog specific as that's
a different forum for different discussion
on that night so I'm bringing that up he
has an example of why I believe that
that checks and balance needs to happen
because I believe that perhaps the authority
has been overstepped for an OK Thank
you. So I think it's appropriate to look
at the what is what the issue is was about
a couple points of clarification if I may
for the chair the I. Was in the I Am A
that vested in the sewer commissioners
water and sewer commissioners with the
authority or ability to sell capacity in
the treatment plan that they were at one
time a contract a party now
a member of the district it was the one
thousand nine hundred six Act and the two
thousand and ten special Act that gave
them out of card. The. Each misspoke
remember the district agreement didn't take
it away. In it didn't interfere with it
it's consistent with the authority they
had it was the two thousand and thirteen
amendment that put the cloud over all of
the authority the sort of measures and
then relative to forty votes in the two
thousand and ten special act that they are
not subject to the district requirement so
it came with the legislation that those
uses didn't work required to be in
a store district as approved by town meeting
to be entitled to store service so it
wasn't something in the I.M.A.
Or the district agreement that exempted
those it was in the legislation Thank you.
It may say something. Going
back to what Jenny had said
and again everything I listen to and
at the expense of sounding like
a broken record. The warrant in the issue
at hand is authority over all authority
of the water and sewer commission. In which
we just keep very away from that and in
to what Jenny said about she would not
support the article. If something isn't done
about it which we're taking one instance
which I don't necessarily agree or
disagree with every comment that's
made here you know it's it's
a good conversation that should be had
personally I think it's the wrong time but
we're introducing that as if it's part
of this article to the general public we
have people talking about
sewer and forty B.
The article was about the authority of the
water and sewer commission and you know
you had mentioned you wouldn't support it
so essentially if that doesn't get done
you're you're not supporting you're.
Telling the public you not supporting the
water and sewer commission having authority
to do any basically do what we were
voted to sit in and do. Well I think if
you listen to Bill's opening statement I
think we are not trying to do that try OK
But when but when she says that she won't
support it and that's that's that's my
issue with it is is it's the the public
probably has
a right to act on whether we have the IT
sole authority whether combined we have
the authority whether to go to town meeting
but isn't that important afterwards I
don't want to mourn article.
Trying to do is sure to hammer out
a mechanism where you guys have for forty
to handle day to day activities with one
of us who just report comes to long term
strategic. Actions that there is there's
a check in basically we get together and
we say does this make sense for the future
of the Tao I think that's where would we
were trying to get to but what with all
the conversation that's been had here I
don't know that the public at home is truly
understanding what's at stake and when
it said that we won't support it over so
over to sewer capacity who
has the authority to sell so
a capacity. I think most people are
understanding that as that's what it pertains
to one ever really doesn't pertain to
all authority and that's why you know
personally you know these these two issues
really need to be separated and people
need to prop up you know be
a bit of vote properly understand one is
complete authority and the other is who
has authority to do you know one particular
thing on manage one particular is I
think is I heard this I heard. It was
compose comments and she said that she
couldn't support without
a mechanism OK So I think that's the key
key language here is that they have that
you could support it provided
there's a mechanism for
a check and balance and so the question
really is what's the level of comfort that
everyone has here tonight as to what that
mechanism is and I don't know what the
mechanism is and I think I really have to
to turn to the legal minds here to figure
that out because I don't know what that
legally can be done if there is there
a binding mechanism that can be
a site separate it aside from the the
action that's it here that gives people
a level of comfort that we can go forward
from here but doesn't that doesn't the
public have
a right to weigh in on that as well and but
by combining these we're asking them to
weigh in. I think the people behind the
discussion tonight is what's really what is
the what is the right mechanism to support
to get to the to your point that you
want to be tested and I don't know what
that is. I understand your point but with
Oh so you know I can make
a suggestion or I think Steve is going
to mix it just what I was just listening
a little bit is the commission it was
one. Proposal floated perhaps of
a side ladder where if that one article
was advancing then maybe the side letter
could. Be that mechanism of whatever the
terms would be whether it be notice to the
Board of Selectmen of
a proposal and the dates that the commissioners
would be considering that and then
members of this like Board could attend.
Just this so that's one form of
means for. Would that be with that type
of agreement be binding in terms of the
fact that there would be. Any type of
proposal like that to sell outside of the
town would involve the opinion of both
boards working together to come with
a majority but
a proof that time was that see that so
that that's the crux of it isn't it I mean
what what this proposal was was notice so
that you'd be aware and then you could
have time then and address your concerns
something more than not I don't know if
the commissioners are willing
to concede that I mean
a lot of them. Michael Christian.
With that is. That just giving notice of
a possible sale outside town. Has
no. It's unilateral whereas
if the situation was selling
inside time in within the
borders you would have to have
a town meeting approval there was an
expectation by the public that they would have
a say in how the sewage was sold in you
and that was one in that I believe that
was the only reason that town meeting
approved it and so why would you think that
town meeting would want to prove inside
the borders but they wouldn't have the
saying that what that they would think would
be OK just to sell outside the borders
in order to help
a neighboring community develop
economically and develop the housing.
Why would why would you think the average
person but growth would think that was OK
. I don't think that's OK And so
what I would what I would say and.
What I will say is work out work
out something when there is
a check and check and balance on the scale
outside just the same way. There is that
family size. And it would have to be that
would have to be worked out before town
meeting so that there is
a guarantee that that process is in
place or that your wiring is considered
a town. That's you need two parties
to switch agreement right so I mean.
The commissioners always had the bizzare
to sell outside of the town without time
meeting under those the legislation but you
know what. Anybody say that did anybody
tell me when they were. When you know when
this was but before tell me did anybody
say Did anybody did any of the water
commission say listen oh by the way what if
you want to hook up inside town we need
anything approval by the way if we want to
sell it to another town we can do it we
don't need anybody over there anybody I
don't think so well I know in the den as
to you know we've got this unique special
Act that allows the town to a staff
with the most times when you have
a public works department or water and
sewer the entire geography of the town is
the district we've got
a unique Act that allows us to create
districts within the town to it makes sense
to me that to make expand or alter those
districts within the time you can bring
you bring it to Tommy. But the just outside
center was always available under the
legislation from eighty
six. Excuse me. But.
Where oh just so you know yes it was
ninety days yes I was in there did not
go over there to tell you Jack you ask
anybody you were doing more street had the
pranks running right. Now and
more street could not work in
excuse might I was one with them so it
was what's unique about the town meeting
approved was because we have these
Internet town districts that's so unusual
otherwise you know the whole town would be
the district and maybe so it wouldn't be
before excuse me I just want our
attorney to speak. Well if you have
a specific question I'm happy to answer
that but the comment I wanted to make was
just that again this comes back to
a policy decision the both both of these
boards and whoever else wants to be
involved I think it's just these two have
to come to an agreement we can certainly
come up with any language that meets your
desires the most recent proposal I just
heard was notice and an opportunity to
be to participate in the hearings which
that's fine but that's not going to address
approval of already that's just an
opportunity to be involved in the discussion
somehow and if that may not be enough
for the Board of Selectmen another
opportunity that you might want to consider
maybe opportunity isn't the right word but
another potential language change. If
this is acceptable to the Board of Selectmen
might be acceptable to the water and
sewer commissioners as the language that
in the article that's proposing to give
the board of selectmen final approval of
four eighty or whatever terminology you
want to be use that involves something
more more than just directory you know
something that's mandatory.
What about considering
a capacity limit whereby the Board of
Selectmen. Gets the final approval authority
if the amount of water and sewer
that sold outside of town is over
a certain capacity I have no idea what that
capacity would be but that's something
that you might want to consider
amongst the two boards. Any
thoughts on that and obviously anything
under that capacity the water and sewer
just takes care of it themselves and
this like we don't have any involvement
approval authority that
might make. Both sides. Of
a complication think we can get to the
point where we can do fine so. Let's go to
town meeting. Join us.
Well that the language
the first. Response of.
The language has been made
a little murky though so it
does have to be clarified so.
The language has been right but also there's
another issue there's another issue
check and balance about selling an asset
this is an asset of the town this is worth
understanding this is this is this is
important to the degree of the of the town
that's why town. Approved it with
the expectation that this was going
to be used for the development of the
town. The economic not the economic
development of the neighboring community
which would boost their economic base body
to fifty percent in housing only it would
put them over the ten percent why should
the town of Foxborough right out
of the game region without without
a marketing flow to entities in town
in tights people bring Why should we
give them water so the ability to see to
sell that asset that we have been waiting
for you is to have if I may go through
you Madam Chair That's why I drafted
a war an article that gave the board of
selectmen that final approval of the
already but the water ensure commissioners
are not happy with it so and so we're
still at an impasse so this overage you
know I think you know there's total
support that all already should be read
all three should be returned as was
originally intended. I think
what we have here is we're in
a new place we have like
a master plan that has evolved over the
past couple of years that. The citizens are
saying that they want their commercial tax
base to grow from Route one it's kind of
a different direction from you know the
concept of selling outside of town and I
think that's where you know this is
coming from it's not I really believe one
hundred percent that involving
the board of selectmen in
a joint decision making process with the
water and sewer commissioners is just
a different way of doing business in because
of this evolution and so I think it
it's
a sensible approach it
doesn't step it does put the
board of selectmen in
a place that they never were before
I understand that but I think that
we're in a different place and this
is an opportunity that. If we just do
a slight adjustment of our course in the
same way that the master plan has adjusted
its course you know the course of what
people are asking for in the town. I think
it can all be addressed in one
fell swoop you know. It's really.
I know it's not simple but it's just it's
a change that's happened over time in
a very short time and I think we're positioned
right now to do the right thing for
everybody by you know having this type of
consensus between the two boards for such
an important asset I don't think
we disagree I think our issue is
it doesn't belong in this war an article
but if it can and I think the attorneys I
believe then if we really can't both here
then we'll both elected boards and the
general public as much as us has
a right to weigh in on this but we're
asking him to weigh in on it now by the way
this this caviar that old if you if you
don't decide to go along with it it's going
to relinquish all the authority so don't
we owe them to clean this up put it
back to where it was meant to
be and then write a war not
a co-op or get together unilaterally and
devise something where the public can
weigh in on in states soley
on the merit of selling to
a capacity whether be inside
a town outside of town how about wherever
the conversation goes I don't think any
of us here disagree with that I just don't
think it's it's where we're playing with
this is the already well most harsh trading
with this authority that was never
meant to be where it is let's put it back
to where it was originally intended to go
and then get together and figure out how
to clean up the other issue because we
don't disagree that that's more you know
warrants conversation and definitely wants
. I think if I just say it's a couple
whites I I think we're just all
a cop in this discussion we don't need this
and I don't think anybody here is doing
it intentionally I think but it's clearly
quite simple it's come down to one piece
of this authority that's it it's that
it's the question of whether or not any
capacity should be sold outside the borders
of this community should that have
a secondary approval process and that's
it and the only opportunity to really do
that is with this amendment back in two to
restore the authority because right now
the authority rests we think rests with
this one so the question then becomes this
is I understand this was willing to
relinquish all authority back to your boy
without question except for that one issue
and that and it's really an important
policy consideration because if we don't
address it now there will be no mechanism
that will later other than to say OK
let's have an agreement to have to have
a hearing where people can tend but their
youth already still rest back with fully
rest back with the boy but what the waters
will commission so that's what the end
of the day I think that's really where the
level of comfort has to be resolved is
is that something that that everyone here
is comfortable with and so far I haven't
heard that this full agreement so I think
we need to come to some resolution of
that and I don't think anybody here is
willing to take is we as expressed any
interest in taking the authority away from
it from the commission I think they're
actually fairly thought of very it's one
of them just what I want aspect somebody.
On just to say Neal Kaiser of love
individual. You know Wing right now.
Scuse me
a few years back I said I
support the water and so
a commission I always have they they always
did an excellent job in this town and
they had many many different awards and
everything else over the last few years. I
got upset with the vote that was taking
by the water and sewer to relinquish
power and now I'm hearing that they want
it back maybe I'm wrong in understanding
what's going on here I went to
a meeting and I told them they
were foolish in doing that and
a few of the gentlemen here tonight
were on that committee they still voted
unanimously to do it. They
should get it back that
power belongs in their pocket they still
present their budget to you like any other
department in the town and then it's
talked over it's gone through the
advisory committee comes in that they
should do the same thing always they need
that control as far as giving it away to
other towns Absolutely not and you will
never get that passed with time and I
am sure every citizen in this town
would come down here and say no
when you talked about Spring Street
and the C.O.
Street going to be answerable. What
was that sewer line going down there
every citizen there wanted
to tie in and they couldn't
any sewer system that comes into this
town and it goes by a residence or
a business that th should be put in period
it should be put in. I don't care who's
paying for it I don't care if and if
development is paying for it if it goes by
a town home
a business the teacher should be put
in in case someone system fails
the Board of Health is going to tell
them to tie in and they should.
A lot of things that you have done in the
town that they people that are having the
sewers in when they're paying for the tell
you the truth every citizen in this town
should be paying for it in some
minute amount you would have
a system and when it goes by your street
regardless of who's putting it in you can
tie into it and that's how it should
be I mean in the past like I say
Gentlemen I'm sorry but you voted against
that and you didn't want to keep your
power and it was
a few years back I went to your meeting and
told you you were crazy please give it
back to them I think they can do the job
and they will include every citizen in
town to let them know what's going on
thank you thank you I want to make
a motion for Neil Kaiser for selectman.
And I can. And thank you for setting up
office today also cable access.
Did you want we just want to know it wasn't
too relevant to that other than I think
any time we issue
a sore extension permit that they require
the wiles to be stopped by the property
so as that. But the. District
agreement has
a provision that allows for. Sale of
capacity among the member towns if
a member times inclined and were
a little concerned about what not knowing
what the proposal would be how does that
comply or conflict with the terms of the
agreement so we'd have to look at that.
It may not but I just don't know
I just want to. Be certain.
Just briefly I don't want to be repetitive
because it was kind of the same circle
but I've been following this for what eight
or nine years even before the I mean
when we're talking about the critical
needs and all through that when I was an
advisor committee in the selectmen all
the time meetings the discussion about
taking big chunks and selling
it to other towns just was not
a discussion you know in the end rich I
understand we're kind of muddying it but
this is
a third meeting that we've had in the last
two meetings we've been giving charging
graphs of the different sewer rates I'm
sorry sewer allowances for different
properties and so we're given that
information over the last two meetings so
whether we wanted to or not where you
know we're in the sewer business over the
last couple months. I don't want to take
anyone's authority out of any other
elected boards or compiler or commissions
rights and powers and valves and pipes
however selling big chunks to
a different town we're kind of brought
into that because we're in somewhat
responsible for the economic development
in our town so we're not so when that the
planning board goes out and does their
exercise with master plans and invites
people and we've got this vision that's
growing in moving but we don't have sewer
for it because we needed to pay
a bill. This would have been
a topic of discussion at the town
meeting that we need to sell
a big chunk to sue or to Sharon or
a lot all over ever but it was just never
discussed so the reason that we're doing
it now is because it's come up through
a process so I'm often given all your power
back except if you want to sell it if
an entity from out of town wants to
purchase it I think it needs to be
a checks and balance whether it was
thought about before or not we're in the
situation and we were given all
this stuff and you know I did spend
a lot of time looking at. The analysis of
the different properties in time out and
who has sewer and what gallonage in some
of it just doesn't make sense and I asked
you know for
a joint meeting with the planning board
and so our commission. And that didn't
happen over the last couple months so I
don't have the answers to feel comfortable
the say take everything back
and then tomorrow there's
a sale to Sharon and his it ten gallons or
one hundred ten thousand gallons I don't
know and I'm not getting straight answers
and I said I read all the memos ever read
all the numbers and it's not making
any sense if you came back with
a program that says all right over the
next two years we've got. Thirty thousand
gallons extra because we've taken all the
allocated flows and adjusted but I'm not
seeing it and rightfully so if we're not
given that information I'm not comfortable
the save run with it he sell it to Sharon
because we get stuck holding the bag if
you can't pay the bill but the other the
water and sewer enterprise if they can see
the bill it falls back on the
the taxpayers because there's
a default and you guys own that not us but
we're here because we were asked to kind
of participate and it's a little bit of
a quagmire so you know it's probably said
five different ways to take all the power
back on for that but not selling
it to another town unless is
a well thought out plan that we can kind
of say great take it because this makes
sense but I don't think we're
there yet right now. I think
I read you had said that
we already so. It's
a blow to the tenets of their. President
his belief that oh that wasn't
a good president it's buys the votes so
concerned in the residents of bucks for oh
I don't know that it's a no and no but
but but yeah but I don't think that's
a good argument that person has been set
just because something was done one time
doesn't mean it was good for the town but
you know I don't think it was good for
the town but folks and you can ask anybody
on Wall Street or the other street loved
this think it was good but. GORDON.
Gordon grain I think that this is
a discussion that probably should have
been How'd. Six months ago it's not
a discussion for a month before
a town meeting it's my opinion that it
does I don't quote go to the floor of
time meeting it would be defeated but it's
an article that needs to be addressed I
believe that the town watch to keep
the authority for some water and so
with water and sewer The only issue that
comes up is just going out of town the
vote the town meeting previously had and I
would strongly recommend that you advise
. That water and sewer withdraw
the article and hold it until the
special town meeting in September and get
dusting resolved so we can all go to town
meeting in lockstep Thank you.
Thank you yes thank you David OK I think
I think all these discussions have
brought up
a very curious point and that is excess
capacity is access capacity really an
asset is an asset if you don't
have the infrastructure to have
a flow do we have the infrastructure in
place to flow what our capacity is today.
And we have infrastructure in place to
flow future capacity excess capacity we
don't know that we have
we have we have. Charts
and excess capacity and what what we
expect to be excess capacity but how we're
going to get from point A to Point B.
Answers. Or Street. Has money
Basset. Hounds get back to you that
you think those days. The more
street quite as plenty of capacity because
none of the capacity that was allocated
for that line and had to be examined at
that time was never sold so that we get
seventy two thousand gallons sitting up
at the end of that that's not coming
through the pipe right now that's the way
it is the town's. Capacity that is the
that the towns area around the common and
and all the way down county street you
know with all the other entity is that we
have on sort of with the exception of C.
Is the states in green view is overcapacity
right now but it's primarily because of
inflow and infiltration I'm
speaking to this you all happen
but what that does is that pays off the
plant. Unfortunately the sewer enterprise
account does not have enough money for us
that even if we discover through an I and
I that we've got problems in the common
area we can't fix it because we don't have
the cash to do it and. Merely doing
this does not bring anything into that
enterprise account that allows us to do
things like that to fix problems in the
system or to address new new entities
for example you know we said that
these entities that come in that are big
commercial I think he's need to provide
their own infrastructure because we don't
have the means to do it and if they
provide their own infrastructure and you
know pay for them for that the gallons per
day they can get into the system so the
answer is part of our system has available
capacity to transport sewer to
Mansfield and to the plant part of
a thousand that's it and we still have the
issue with the master plan with some of
those other economic development areas
getting flow across town so I think there's
a there's
a bigger discussion that needs to happen
specifically with silica pasty and what is
capacity. I think. Gordon
might be correct you know. We
come up with
a war Arkell the pulls out the sale
of capacity to. Outside our borders
Well we table until the fall thinking.
It would the Board of Selectmen entertain
a joint committee between water and sewer
in the selectmen with equal votes to deal
with this one issue and then clean up the
water an article to deal with everything
else. From a town meeting. From
a town meeting I suggested How about I
mean if you if you say table this still.
Yes actually I think we're getting somewhere
now to to cover the town to carve out
the know that these two committees would
get together and mutually decide if that
was
a good idea is two committees would take
equal number of members and put them on
a joint committee that would meet
solely for the purpose of the L.
And I think that's where the weapon began
this discussion it's getting somewhere.
Otherwise I'd work if I'm wrong because if
we table the Senate doesn't do anything
in town meeting with you guys and we still
mission I think everybody the people who
voted for what reason if we don't
want to be addressed in the form of
a floor Amendment right away which to the
existing war I don't recall establishing
a joint committee but. You know look we
dressed the article says he was Chancellor
of the new school there without me. I'm
sorry go ahead I'm sorry I was going to
repeat the question please so I thought
the question was Should we move to amend
the motion to include the joint committee
to address that but the one articles
about authorization for such
legislation so I think you can do
a joint committee. On your own at Town
Council agrees but like you don't need it I
mean vote to establish
a joint committee to study this issue and
see if you can come to terms. Right that
might be slightly outside the scope of the
article in the warrants already closed
so it's possible we could have
a motion from town meeting for that does
something with respect to the authority
part of it but we can't create a
separate committee and I think that's
a good idea it sounds like
that's getting towards
a solution but I don't think it would be
within the scope of the war in article to
make that change separately it may be
possible that we. Without the town meeting
create an ad hoc committee and and then
give it. However many you know if you want
all eight of you five so on the three
of you if you just want to take
a majority of each of those members on
then have equal approval farty if that's
something you all agree on there's a way
we can make that work can I just ask
a question the the urgency between
rushing it and getting it on May first
extending it to have it on
a. Special time meeting and I'm missing
something is our contract waiting to be
signed that we had those extra months we've
been given the opinion that anything we
do or act on as one of those will
commissioners could be in question so you're
That's what I understand that's what I'm
saying are you guys working on something
that is going to be a
question that can't wait
a few months and anything we vote
on from an abatement to. Meat
meaning man and song essentially could be
brought into question so that's OK. If I
could for you just I think it's important
you do before in the article or sooner
rather than later for all the things that
we just talked about but it's and to I
think it's possible that I'll defer to
counsel on this that this part of the motion
what's good said is that is that the
that the that they move to approve the
authority as stated in the in the to two
thousand the Act of two thousand and ten
two thousand and six. Is that correct
Steve yes and in that with the
exception that any sale capacity outside
the borders would be subject to further
review by
a joint committee joint committee so you
single you can carve that topic out of
that motion here because right now the at
the current the current authority gives
gives the commission the entire three
thought over all sales. Capacity that's the
issue right now but the powers can go back
to the commission but you're just going
to carve out that once I want the one
topic is that possible to do that I don't
know they are not I'm
a logical perspective you're going to be
on legal fees which I don't know I don't
know if I heard exactly what that language
would be like if you could be that for
local approval for legislation if there's
some uncertainty in it and then we dance
that to the legislature
would they accept it as
a local approval or town meeting depends
on what your language was. That might make
it so I suspect if if it
said it's something to be
a player to be named later and then we do
that no legislation Council at the house
might say right that's not my approval and
I don't know that's just I think what I
was suggesting is that the motion at our
meeting on the article would be that that
it be be approved be so approved with the
exception of any sale of capacity outside
the time so a capacity
as i shall we say with
a further review. By by by special commission
Oh I think it's not adding that to
the actual you know more about it right
but just by the motion and I think
impending on the final language which I
know I gave you I wore an article we then
tweeted
a little bit further I haven't seen
whatever you've finally got on the war it's
a Depending on what the languages you can
make the motion narrower to be something
within the article and you can't explain
you can't broaden it at all and make
something more specific with respect to
another committee or whatever the approval
it already is going to
be but you can eliminate
a small portion of what's in there.
Like you think you get. The ones.
And
a warning of your create you know I gave
it to the slide thank you right you know
it was it was there with the other meetings
ago with two means ago you know what
you want to read you want to.
Hear it yeah. That's OK but
I can really play so that it says that the
to authorize the war to select in the
fall of the General Court
a petition for specialist lation to clarify
the executive powers of the town's
water and sewer commission is by amending
Chapter five the exit two thousand and
four entitled An act providing
for a select when Tommy to form
a government in the town Fox rubber
revising Section three subparts
a set out to read as follows new text is
on the line. He says Section three A He's
actually
a positon should be vested in the board
of selectmen in the act referred to as is
the B.O.'s who shall have all the powers
given in the boards of the selectmen by
general laws except for those executive
powers granted to time engine except for
those executive powers granted
to the town's board of water so
a commission has by chapter forty six of
the acts apply to this I were provided
provided however that all personal collective
bargaining powers of the Waters who
commissioners shall be vested in the tell
me that there was something new. And
provided for there however the voices like
mentioned have final authority over any
sales to it because of the that was the
thing that we talked about the way they
mean to property and that's where we treat
their living for there are so property
outside of town borders so very. So that
was the article that I provided and my
understanding was that only these are part
of it for the from the perspective of
the wire in circulation degraded want to
get that so instead of the word final
should have the joint. But if this is
what you put on the warrant then that
line which I gave to you from what has it
in his No one has an agenda you know this
is not this is not been we haven't actually
filed the war yeah I mean it's been
votes and shared with everybody right
everybody's every read it but this is the
article that's in there now so we haven't
changed anything that's been filed as
soon as they submitted. So the question
is can we can we send them or not and can
we put together a warrant
a motion that will address
this issue. There's
a possible you know I'm the only mechanism
to do that is on the floor. If the
moderator declares it within the scope of
the article but I had understood that you
were going to include that extra provision
that I provided about with that other
exception that you don't don't have to
be another motion on the floor of the
meeting to that language reality and they're
going to get enough of that to get you
know that you're right so it was corrected
for later i guess if the moderator says
it's within the scope of the article.
Which I wrote in my opinion it could be
considered to be within the scope because
it's one exception to the power that
you're getting back to that right now that
the paralyzed from the selectmen whether
that was intended or not that's where this
and so the article the purpose of the
article was to try to give the power back
to the water and sewer commission. With
those two exceptions the one that's in there
and then the additional one regarding
the sale of capacity outside of town since
that one didn't make it in there in my
opinion that would be within the scope
because the scope was broader but that would
be
a call for the moderator over. The
top about his decision. Which
would I'm sorry but what do you think
of that language he added language you
know. It ends up and. It ends up
being those two exceptions it's the
employees and then a joint decision
a joint authority I think it if it's joint.
And we agree to it if if it's sold to
the. Selectmen then that's what we
initially had an issue with. I think the
intention is to have
a joint correct. But I'd also say
whatever how whatever is the cleanest
presentation of it I think is the way
should be read be right we're all going for
a yes I think we can work on
a motion for that that we can both review
it with everybody the last thing we want
to end up what is sitting here. Two months
two years from now exact mind out that
it could be construed in
a way that it wasn't represented to be and
we want to we we clearly want to make
sure that the language is clear his is
appropriate but I would also like to say
that language is. Standard language isn't
there I would like to have the Board of
Water storage approve it and
if somebody at town meetings
because I was not like to
see Sunday morning so it's
a you know we should we should not we're
not going to support this and then that.
And I think we're given every indication
we support that's what I hope so. We
proposed because the crisis out of
that I do not think you can you read
a piece of well I can you know I just
I just made a note to myself to draft
a motion under. So it will be.
Starting back from the very beginning
I move that we are after is the border
slot going to file the General Court
a petition for special interest lation
to clarify the executive powers of the
town's water and sewer Commissioners by
a man in chapter five of the acts of
two thousand and four entitled An act
providing for
a selectman had been town manager form of
government in the town of Foxborough very
much as in section three sub part of said
Act read as follows in the new Texas
underline Section three A executive powers
of the town to be vested in the board of
selectmen in this act referred to as Board
of Selectmen for outside below us who
shall have all the powers given to boards
of slope and by the general laws except
for those executive powers granted to
the town manager and except for those
executive powers granted to the boards
I'm sorry the town's Board of Water and
Sewer Commissioners by chapter forty six
of the Acts of one nine hundred eighty six
and provided further however. That all
personal and collective bargaining powers of
the town and sewer commissioner shall be
vested with the town manager and this is
where and they play messy notes
provided further however that. All
sale of water and sewer capacity outside
of town shall be subject to joint approval
of the board of selectmen and water and
sewer commission. And I don't think you'd
want water power here just. To
a private party would you. That's what
I would say because you know you have
a whole series of those at the minute if
the talent Sharon is purchasing it for
their private development. Why wouldn't why
would you want to put private I want to
begin to. Sell it to Mansfield
feeling nor to you just so.
They could be sold to share.
With you believe it is.
Linda thanks Linda was a planned out. Just
a quick question I think of that he
answered but I just want to clarify
a couple weeks ago when we having this
discussion you folks are having this
discussion it came up about the
board is like men having. A say
in the billboards funding and everything
and revenue that's gone away then that's
back to the water and so are correct
there was always with it was
a mission there was always
with right but you had made
a comment about no no I think the clarify
that I'd say only that we've had some
discussions about the possible possibility
we're not it's not just with this board
though we've been talking
I was talking with
a water so commission that Lorraine did
make and that your comment you're referring
to my comment about the water tower Yes
that's not part of this discussion. Not
part of this discussion and won't be part
of this article either you know not to
the water and so are crap it was always
with water and you're right it was.
So high street the town councils original
amendment to the warrant was all sale of
sewer. And then you just add it outside
of town. So where does that leave us
in terms of outside of the sewer district
sales of sewer capacity outside of the
sewer district that there remains
unchanged Earth or is the same as it was
a car is always was so that authority is
as it will go back to the saw with this
remember it will go back to this water sewer
commission I believe the select woman
said that at the Town Meeting understanding
was that sale outside of the sewer
district had to be approved by town meeting
still that's correct that's things that
will still sponsor Thank you. Tracey.
Tracey the silly chair the advisory
committee we are having our last meeting
tomorrow which I know all you where because
I think I've met with you all many
times over the past couple weeks so we're
going to need this wording just from
a timing perspective you know the expectation
to that it and to vote on it in one
evening is it's going to be
kind of difficult you've got
a couple of topics we need to discuss
tomorrow so I just want to put it out there
that we're up against crunch time we've
also got to get things to the paper in the
write ups done so if you can just be aware
that I know we're twenty four hours away
but we are dealing with some tough time
things from stinking thinking so I'm
rich can we. Come to
a consensus here that this is the
language will bring forward we'll have
a typed and ready for advisory committee
tomorrow and we can all agree that we
support this. Larry. And somebody will get
it over to the moderator because I think
he's got to he has to be going to us
before they can yes he'll come you know it
took us through what's your thought and.
So what we're going to need tonight yes
Bill do you think we should take any type
of vote on this. I think that they this
should be
a vote on both from both wars that will
support the language as discussed and I can
remember as this goes through I.
Think John you will make most of.
It's what article is this it's. About twenty
five OK I move the ball select accept
Article twenty five. Has recently
discussed and as amended.
And this is Article twenty five is the
executive power of town water and sewer
commissioners. Second
second any discussion
all those in favor I.
Assure. You. If you go. To.
You know. We just haven't read just because
I think you're after it entirely and
try to read up my notes college or
maybe just last year I got rated as
a result I know just the getting and yeah
I know why they might write you know that
I'm not. For that too so that was the
provided they're. Provided further
however that any sale of sewer capacity
outside of town shall be subject to the
joint approval of the board of selectmen
and water and sewer commission. To so will
. Make into
a motion spec of motion with the
second discussion on favor I. Very
much thank you all very
much thank you. John.
Very good. Very good.
Because you have some action items which
help you to get what you know I don't
think you know. We have
a history. Because they were they
were supposed to respect others in.
The first action that is going to guide
you to me very much against regular Joes
raise it with support I move that the Bush
like and approved the application for
the May thirtieth two thousand and fifteen
they were fifty in your Foxboro against
diabetes road race. Also. Before
any discussion of all those in favor
of right. The next is in regard to
a donation to the board library
a move that the boys like men approve the
donation of the one hundred fifty dollars
to the Boyd library from Richard B.
Lynn in thank Mr Olin for his donation
second to all those who pay for my.
Work in the last Titan is in regard to the
boy library donation was I moved at the
Board of Selectmen approved the donation
of one hundred dollars to the boys in the
library from the teach shows that miniature
club in thank them for their donation
so all those in favor.
Of it like. I think that
everything on our agenda. Gives them
a commotion to address. Nine
twenty three weeks from
a society Second for those in
favor. Thanks everybody good night.